Narrator: Part 4
William: The windmill’s frame weighed about 90lb,
and I knew the only way we would get it to the top of the tower we’d built was to use a rope and pulley.
I used my mother’s thick clothesline wire instead.
We fastened it to the windmill’s bamboo handle.
Taking the other end, I climbed the tower and hooked the wire over the top rung,
then dropped it down to Gilbert.
Geoffrey stood below on the middle rungs to guide the machine as it went up.
Standing there, I could see over the acacia tree to where the fields joined the highlands.
‘OK, Gilbert,’ I yelled. ‘Bring it up!’
Carefully, he pulled the wire.
First, the windmill’s handle lifted, then the frame rose and wobbled.
Little by little, the windmill made its way up the tower.
With each pull, it swung and banged its cumbersome blades against the tower’s wood frame.
When the handle came within reach, I grabbed hold and screamed, ‘Tie it down!’ …
Once the windmill was fastened, we looked at each other and smiled.
It felt sturdy and very strong. Sweat poured down my face.
I could hardly wait to watch the blades spin.
While Geoffrey made his way down the tower, I remained atop my perch.
To the north, I could see the iron- sheet roofs of the trading centre
and the brown row of huts that sat behind the main road.
Then something strange began to happen...